<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Mexico</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Ustawienia</string>
    <string name="action_go_web">Chrome</string>
    <string name="action_ccreate_order">Złóż Zamówienie</string>

    <string name="action_share">Udostępnij</string>
    <string name="title_top">Fragment TopFragment</string>

    <string name="open_drawer">Otwórz Szufladę</string>
    <string name="close_drawer">Zamknij Szufladę</string>

    <string name="overview_teotihuacan">Teotihuacan – stanowisko archeologiczne położone na centralnym płaskowyżu, na północny wschód od miasta Meksyk. Nazwa stanowiska pochodzi z języka nahuatl i można ją przetłumaczyć jako: miejsce, w którym ludzie stają się bogami. Równocześnie jest to nazwa kultury, której wpływ na inne ludy Mezoameryki był przemożny.\"
    Miasto zostało nazwane przez Azteków „Teotihuacán”, czyli miejscem, z którego pochodzą bogowie; miejscem, gdzie rodzą się bogowie lub miejscem, w którym ludzie stają się bogami. Nastąpiło to ok. 500 lat po jego upadku</string>


    <string name="history_teotihuacan">Według legend zostało ono zbudowane przez olbrzymów, zwanych quinametin, którzy mieli żyć przed pojawieniem się ludzi i zostali zniszczeni przez wielką katastrofę. Na terenie płaskowyżu, od II w. p.n.e. do II w. n.e. powstało wielkie prekolumbijskie centrum religijne związane z kulturą ludów Mezoameryki. Wokół centrum ceremonialnego i religijnego istniało miasto, którego największy rozkwit przypada na IV-VII w. Jego część mieszkalna została zaplanowana na prostokątnej siatce ulic. Przeprowadzono regulację rzeki San Juan, zbudowano zbiorniki wody deszczowej. W kompleksie miejskim powstały place targowe, spichlerze, teatry i boiska do gry w pelotę. Plan urbanistyczny miasta miał układ dwuosiowy. Jedna z osi była w kierunku północ – południe i miała nazwę Aleja Zmarłych, druga oś ciągnęła się ze wschodu na zachód. Według współczesnych szacunków liczba mieszkańców określana jest na ok. 200 tys. Do IX w. Wpływy centrum obejmowały całą centralną część Wyżyny Meksykańskiej.\n\n
    To święte miasto było celem pielgrzymek wielu plemion żyjących w Mezoameryce. Według mitów indiańskich tu powstał świat, nastąpiło oddzielenie światła od ciemności, powstało słońce i księżyc. Najprawdopodobniej w Teotihuacan powstał system religijny przyjęty później przez inne plemiona, tu kapłani opracowali kalendarz, według którego liczono czas.\n\n
    Kultura Teotihuacán została podzielona na cztery okresy archeologiczne:\n Teotihuacán I Tzacualli (600 r. p.n.e. - 200 r. p.n.e.) – okres kultury będącej pod wpływem ośrodków Choluli, El Tapalcate, Calchicomula. W I w. p.n.e. największe znaczenie osiągają Cuicuilco i Teotihuacán zbudowane na przeciwnych brzegach jeziora Texcoco. Występuje ceramika o charakterystycznej polichromii negatywnej, okres wznoszenia pierwszych piramid i zasiedlenia Oztoyahualco. Jedynym bogiem znanym z tego okresu jest bóg deszczu, pierwowzór późniejszego Tlaloka.\n
    Teotihuacán II Miccaotli (200 r. p.n.e. - 250 r. n.e.) – okres którego centrum było Azcapotzalco i jego wpływy sięgały m.in. do Choluli i Morelos. W okresie tym rozwinęły się ośrodki w Tres Zapotes, Monte Alban II-III, El Tajin. Powstały freski w Superpuestos, rozwinął się kult Tlaloka i powstała świątynia Quetzalcoatla.\n
    Teotihuacán III Tlamilolpa-Xolalpan (250 r. - 650 r.) – okres rozkwitu i supremacji Teotihuacánu nad całą Doliną Meksykańską, handlu z ośrodkami na całym obszarze Mezoameryki, być może wypraw zdobywczych na ziemiach Majów.\n
    Teotihuacán III Ahuizolta-Amantla (650 r. - 900 r.) – okres rozwoju świadomości religijnej, wzrost znaczenia bóstw i rytuałów składania ofiar z ludzi. Powolny upadek miasta i zastąpienie kultury Teotihuacán kulturą toltecką i przeniesienie głównych ośrodków religijnych do Tula.\n\n Kultura Teotihuacán oddziaływała w sensie kulturowym i religijnym na całą Mezoamerykę, aż do dzisiejszej Gwatemali. Niektórzy naukowcy twierdzą, że mieszkańcy Teotihuacán wysyłali ekspedycje wojskowe dla podboju innych plemion, inni zaś, że ich wpływ był pokojowy – poprzez kontakty handlowe i eksport idei. W miastach Zapoteków, Totonaków i Majów znaleziono siedziby przedstawicieli Teotihuacánu – kupców lub przedstawicieli elit.\n\n
    Z drugiej strony niektóre zwyczaje mieszkańców Teotihuacánu pozostały na zawsze związane tylko z tym miejscem. Na przykład jedynie tu chowano zmarłych w pozycji zgiętej pod posadzkami domów[1].
    Bogactwo Teotihuacán wzięło się prawdopodobnie z eksploatacji złóż obsydianu w pobliskiej miejscowości Pachuca oraz Otumba. Mimo, że Otumba było położone ok. 15 km od Teotihuacán, jego mieszkańcy woleli sprowadzać obsydian z Pachuca, odległego o ok. 50 km.\n\n
    Obsydian był przerabiany na narzędzia, uważane za luksusowe. Były to ostrza noży, groty strzał, czy ozdoby. Rzemieślnicy różnych profesji zamieszkiwali osobne dzielnice, podobnie jak w średniowiecznej Europie. Były one rozmieszczone wokół centrum ceremonialno-świątynnego, zamieszkanego przez elity władzy – kapłanów, kupców, wojowników. W dzielnicach rzemieślniczych znaleziono warsztaty ceramiczne, tkackie, obróbki obsydianu, a nawet świątynie poświęcone bogom opiekującym się danym rzemiosłem. Często mieszkali tam ludzie z innych regionów, utrzymujących kontakty z Teotihuacánem. Na peryferiach mieszkali chłopi.\n\n
    Z innych rejonów Mezoameryki sprowadzano kakao, kauczuk, muszle morskie, barwne pióra ptaków tropikalnych, przede wszystkim quetzala i papug oraz futra i to pochodzące zarówno z południowego wschodu – z Gwatemali, jak i z północy – z południowych Stanów Zjednoczonych.\n
    Dodatkowym źródłem bogactwa były pielgrzymki z wielu rejonów do centrum ceremonialnego i religijnego.\n\n
    W okresie rozkwitu nie było w Kotlinie Meksykańskiej miasta, które mogłoby konkurować z Teotihuacánem. On sam zaś kontrolował wiele miast, np. El Tajin, Copan, Altun Ha, Tikal, Kaminaljujú i wiele mniejszych ośrodków rozrzuconych nad Zatoką Meksykańską, na półwyspie Jukatan, aż po dzisiejszy Honduras i Belize.\n
    Podczas gdy w innych ośrodkach wiele przedstawień malarskich czy rzeźbiarskich dotyczyło królów, dynastii i wojen, sztuka Teotihuacánu była poświęcona wyłącznie religii. Z kolej skąpa ilość napisów, i to wyłącznie kalendarzowych, nie pozwala nam nazwać przedstawianych bogów. Można ich było zidentyfikować jedynie przez porównanie do przedstawień azteckich.\n
    Nie wiemy natomiast nic o ludziach zamieszkujących to wielkie centrum, skąd pochodzili, jakim mówili językiem i co się z nimi stało. Wiele lat później Totonakowie znad Zatoki Meksykańskiej mówili, że to ich przodkowie byli założycielami Teotihuacán, ale nie da się tego potwierdzić. Aztekowie również twierdzili, że ich przodkowie wywodzą się z Teotihuacánu.\n\n
    W VII w. centrum Teotihuacánu zostało częściowo zniszczone podczas pożaru. Dzielnice rzemieślnicze nie uległy zniszczeniu. Po pożarze miasto nie wróciło do dawnej świetności. Wyroby rzemieślnicze były coraz gorszej jakości. Stopniowo opuszczane poddało się kolejnym napaściom koczowniczych plemion północy. Prawdopodobnie zostało zajęte przez Tolteków, a później Chichimeków. W X w. zostało opuszczone. Za spadkobierców kultury Teotihuacanu uważa się Tolteków oraz Azteków.</string>


    <string name="overview_cholula">Cholula (Nahuatl languages: Cholōllān) was an important city of pre-Columbian Mesoamerica, dating back to at least the 2nd century BCE, with settlement as a village going back at least some thousand years earlier. The site of Cholula is just west of the modern city of Puebla and served as a trading outpost. Its immense pyramid is the largest such structure in the Americas, and the largest pyramid structure by volume in the world.Cholula is one of the key religious centers of ancient Mexico.\n\n
Cholula is located in the Puebla-Tlaxcala Valley of the central Mexican highlands. It is surrounded to the west by the snow-covered peaks Popocatepetl and Iztaccihuatl, and Malinche to the north. The summer rainy season and the melted snow in winter provide a great environment for irrigation agriculture. There is also a confluence of several perennial streams with the Atoyac River that creates a wetland to the north and east of the urban center. This has resulted in abundant and excellent agriculture during the colonial period, which led to Cholula being known as the richest agricultural region in central Mexico. Maize is the major crop cultivated but they also harvested maguey, chiles, and cochineal for dye. The soil is rich in clay, which made pottery and brick-making an important part of their economy. Textiles and elaborate decorative capes were also popular.\n\n
Cholula\’s strategical location in the center of the Mexican highlands gives it a prime place as a trade outpost. Here, trade routes connected the Gulf coast, the Valley of Mexico, Tehuacan Valley, and La Mixteca Baja through Izucar de Matamoros. From there, trade routes went to the Pacific coast, where the longer Pacific Coast communication and trade route existed.\n\n
Because of its location, Cholula served as the link center where primary trade routes and alliance corridors linked Post-Classic groups of Tolteca-Chichimeca kingdoms with southern Mesoamerica.\n\n
Textiles were of extreme importance for Cholula\’s economy. During the Postclassic period they were a common unit of tribute and exchange. Textiles were manufactured for local consumption and traded extensively by different merchants that frequented the city. Textile production accounts are provided by ethnohistorical and archaeological sources. Spanish writings from Colonial times have noted their excellence in dying techniques and ability to dye wool threads in diverse colors to produce a variety of textiles. Some of the materials they used were cotton, which was probably imported from the Gulf Coast or Southern Puebla, and maguey, feathers, rabbit fur, tree silk, milkweed, and human hair that were all locally found. Artifacts such as spindle whorls found at different Cholula site loci provide evidence for the extensive production of textiles in the site. These are rare from the Formative and the Classic periods but become more prevalent in the Postclassic. Only unbaked-clay whorls may have been used during the earlier periods but these are not preserved in the archaeological record. The high concentration of spindle whorls recovered from Cholula in comparison to other Mesoamerican sites attests to the important role they played in their economy.</string>


    <string name="history_cholula">Cholula grew from a very small village to a regional center between CE 600 and 700 ce. During this period, Cholula was a major center contemporaneous with Teotihuacan and seems to have avoided, at least partially, that city\'s fate of violent destruction at the end of the Mesoamerican Classic period.\n\n
The earliest occupation dates back to the Early Formative period. In the 1970s, Mountjoy discovered a waterlogged deposit dating to the late Middle Formative period near the ancient lakeshore. The earliest construction evidence at Cholula dates to the Late Formative period. Initial stages of the Great Pyramid probably date to the Terminal Formative Period and show stylistic resemblance to early Teotihuacan. Estimates suggest that during the Formative period the site extended for about 2 square kilometers, with a population of five to ten thousand.\n\n
The Classical period is known for the construction of the Great Pyramid. At least stages 3 and 10 were built during this period and many other mounds of the urban zone, like the Cerro Cocoyo, Edificio Rojo, San Miguelito and the Cerro Guadalupe, were also constructed at this point in time. The central ceremonial precinct included the Great Pyramid, a big plaza to the west, and the Cerro Cocoyo as the west most pyramid of the plaza group. Classical period Cholula most likely covered around 5 square kilometers, and had an estimated population of fifteen to twenty thousand individuals.\n\n
During the Early Postclassic there might have been an ethnic change, suggested by the influx of Gulf Coast motifs and by the burial at the pyramid of an individual with Maya-style cranial modification and inlaid teeth.\n\n
Cholula reached its maximum size and population during the Postclassic period. It covered 10 square kilometers and had a population of thirty to fifty thousand. During this period, ethnic changes divide the historical sequence into two phases: the Tlachihualtepetl and Cholollan phases. The Tlachihualtepetl phase (CE 700–1200) is named after the city of the Great Pyramid as it was recorded in the Historia Tolteca-Chichimeca ethnohistoric source. During this phase according to the ethnohistoric accounts, Cholula was taken over by the Gulf Coast group known as the Olmec-Xicallanca, who made it their capital. From there, they controlled the high plateau of Puebla and Tlaxcala. Under this group, the potters of Cholula began to develop the fine polychrome wares that were to become the most popular vessels in all of ancient Mexico.\n\n
In CE 1200, ethnic Tolteca-Chichimeca conquered Cholula. At this point, the Patio of the Altars was destroyed and the ceremonial center (with the \“new\” Pyramid of Quetzalcoatl) was moved to the present zócalo (main plaza) of Cholula. Polycrome pottery from this phase used distinctive design configurations but was derived from the earlier styles. The “laca” pottery also dates to this period.\n\n
During this entire period, Cholula remained a regional center of importance, enough so that, at the time of the fall of the Aztec Empire, Aztec princes were still formally anointed by a Cholulan priest.\n\n
At the time of the arrival of Hernán Cortés, Cholula was second only to the Aztec capital Tenochtitlan (modern Mexico City) as the largest city in central Mexico, possibly with a population of up to 100,000 people. In addition to the great temple of Quetzalcoatl and various palaces, the city had 365 temples.\n\n
In 1519, Cortes and his troops were allowed to rest and stay in the city on their way to Tenochtitlan, however, at the request of Montezuma II, the Cholulans began plotting an ambush to kill the Spaniards. Trenches and holes with spikes were prepared and women and children evacuated. Upon this discovery, Cortes had the main warriors and nobles brought to him, had them massacred at the central plaza and partially burned the city to make an example of the Cholulans for what he considered treason.\n\n
A few years later, Cortés vowed that the city would be rebuilt with a Christian church to replace each of the old pagan temples. Fewer than 50 new churches were actually built, but the Spanish colonial churches are unusually numerous for a city of its size. There is a common saying in Cholula that there is a church for every day of the year.\n\n
During the Spanish colonial period, Cholula was overtaken in importance by the nearby newly-founded Spanish city of Puebla.</string>


    <string name="overview_monte_alban">Monte Albán is a large pre-Columbian archaeological site in the Santa Cruz Xoxocotlán Municipality in the southern Mexican state of Oaxaca (17.043° N, 96.767°W). The site is located on a low mountainous range rising above the plain in the central section of the Valley of Oaxaca, where the latter\'s northern Etla, eastern Tlacolula, and southern Zimatlán and Ocotlán (or Valle Grande) branches meet. The present-day state capital Oaxaca City is located approximately 9 km (6 mi) east of Monte Albán.\n\n
The partially excavated civic-ceremonial center of the Monte Albán site is situated atop an artificially leveled ridge. It has an elevation of about 1,940 m (6,400 ft) above mean sea level and rises some 400 m (1,300 ft) from the valley floor, in an easily defensible location. In addition to the monumental core, the site is characterized by several hundred artificial terraces, and a dozen clusters of mounded architecture covering the entire ridgeline and surrounding flanks. The archaeological ruins on the nearby Atzompa and El Gallo hills to the north are traditionally considered to be an integral part of the ancient city as well.\n\n
Besides being one of the earliest cities of Mesoamerica, Monte Albán was important for nearly one thousand years as the pre-eminent Zapotec socio-political and economic center. Founded toward the end of the Middle Formative period at around 500 BC, by the Terminal Formative (ca.100 BC-AD 200) Monte Albán had become the capital of a large-scale expansionist polity that dominated much of the Oaxacan highlands and interacted with other Mesoamerican regional states, such as Teotihuacan to the north (Paddock 1983, Marcus 1983). The city lost its political pre-eminence by the end of the Late Classic (ca. AD 500-750), and soon thereafter was largely abandoned. Small-scale reoccupation, opportunistic reuse of earlier structures and tombs, and ritual visitations marked the archaeological history of the site into the Colonial period.\n\n
The etymology of the site\'s present-day name is unclear. Tentative suggestions regarding its origin range from a presumed corruption of a native Zapotec name to a colonial-era reference to a Spanish soldier by the name Montalbán or to the Alban Hills of Italy. The ancient Zapotec name of the city is not known, as abandonment occurred centuries before the writing of the earliest available ethnohistorical sources.</string>


    <string name="history_monte_alban">Being visible from anywhere in the central part of the Valley of Oaxaca, the impressive ruins of Monte Albán attracted visitors and explorers throughout the colonial and modern eras. Among others, Guillermo Dupaix investigated the site in the early 19th century CE, J. M. García published a description of the site in 1859, and A. F. Bandelier visited and published further descriptions in the 1890s. A first intensive archaeological exploration of the site was conducted in 1902 by Leopoldo Batres, then General Inspector of Monuments for the Mexican government under Porfirio Diaz.\n\n
It was not until 1931 that large-scale scientific excavations were undertaken, under the direction of Mexican archaeologist Alfonso Caso. In 1933, Eulalia Guzmán assisted with the excavation of Tomb 7. Over the following eighteen years, Caso and his colleagues Ignacio Bernal and Jorge Acosta excavated large sections within the monumental core of the site. Much of what is visible today in areas open to the public was reconstructed at that time. Besides resulting in the excavation of a large number of residential and civic-ceremonial structures and hundreds of tombs and burials, one lasting achievement of the project by Caso and his colleagues was the establishment of a ceramic chronology (phases Monte Albán I through V) for the period between the site\'s founding in ca. 500 BCE to end of the Postclassic period in CE 1521.\n\n
The investigation of the periods preceding Monte Albán\'s founding was a major focus in the late 1960s of the Prehistory and Human Ecology Project started by Kent Flannery of the University of Michigan. Over the following two decades, this project documented the development of socio-political complexity in the valley from the earliest Archaic period (ca. 8000-2000 BCE) to the Rosario phase (700-500 BCE) immediately preceding Monte Albán. It set the stage for an understanding of the latter\'s founding and developmental trajectory. In this context, among the major accomplishments of Flannery\'s work in Oaxaca are his extensive excavations at the important formative center of San José Mogote in the Etla branch of the valley, a project co-directed with Joyce Marcus of the University of Michigan.\n\n
A further important step in the understanding of the history of occupation of the Monte Albán site was reached with the Prehistoric Settlement Patterns in the Valley of Oaxaca Project begun by Richard Blanton and several colleagues from the University of Michigan in the early 1970s. Their intensive survey and mapping of the entire site demonstrated the full scale and size of Monte Albán, beyond the limited area which had been explored by Caso. Subsequent seasons of the same project under the direction of Blanton, Gary Feinman, Steve Kowalewski, Linda Nicholas, and others extended the survey coverage to practically the entire valley, producing an invaluable amount of data on the region\'s changing settlement patterns from the earliest times to the arrival of the Spanish in CE 1521\n\n
As indicated by Blanton\'s survey of the site, the Monte Albán hills appear to have been uninhabited prior to 500 BCE (the end of the Rosario ceramic phase). At that time, San José Mogote was the major population center in the valley and base of a chiefdom that likely controlled much of the northern Etla branch. Perhaps as many as three or four other, smaller chiefly centers controlled other sub-regions of the valley, including Tilcajete in the southern Valle Grande branch and Yegüih in the Tlacolula arm to the east. Competition and warfare seem to have characterized the Rosario phase. The regional survey data suggests the existence of an unoccupied buffer zone between the San José Mogote chiefdom and those to the south and east.\n\n
It is within this no-man\'s land that Monte Albán was founded at the end of the Rosario period and it quickly reached a population estimate of around 5,200 by the end of the following Monte Albán Ia phase (ca.300 BCE). This remarkable population increase was accompanied by an equally rapid decline at San José Mogote and neighbouring satellite sites, making it likely that its chiefly elites were directly involved in the founding of the future Zapotec capital. This rapid shift in population and settlement, from dispersed localized settlements to a central urban site in a previously unsettled area, has been referred to as the \“Monte Alban Synoikism\” by Marcus and Flannery, p. 140–146 in reference to similar recorded instances in the Mediterranean area in antiquity.\n\n
Although it was previously thought that a similar process of large-scale abandonment, and thus participation in the founding of Monte Albán, occurred at other major chiefly centers, such as Yegüih and Tilcajete, at least in the latter\'s case this now appears to be unlikely. A recent project directed by Charles Spencer and Elsa Redmond of the American Museum of Natural History in New York has shown that, rather than being abandoned, the site grew significantly in population during the periods Monte Albán Early I and Late I (ca. 500-300 BCE and 300-100 BCE, respectively). Tilcajete might have actively opposed incorporation into the increasingly powerful Monte Albán state.\n\n
By the beginning of the Terminal Formative (Monte Albán II phase, ca. 100 BCE-CE 200), Monte Albán had an estimated population of 17,200 making it one of the largest Mesoamerican cities at the time. As its political power grew, Monte Albán expanded militarily, through cooption, and via outright colonization, into several areas outside the Valley of Oaxaca, including the Cañada de Cuicatlán to the north and the southern Ejutla and Sola de Vega valleys. During this period and into the subsequent Early Classic (Monte Albán IIIA phase, ca. CE 200-500), Monte Albán was the capital of a major regional polity that exerted a dominating influence over the Valley of Oaxaca and across much of the Oaxacan highlands. Evidence at Monte Albán is suggestive of high-level contacts between the site\'s elites and those at the powerful central Mexican city of Teotihuacan, where archaeologists have identified a neighbourhood inhabited by ethnic Zapotecs from the valley of Oaxaca. By the Late Classic (Monte Albán IIIB/IV, ca. CE 500-1000), the site\'s influence outside and inside the valley declined. Elites at several other centers, once part of the Monte Albán state, began to assert their autonomy, including sites such as Cuilapan and Zaachila in the Valle Grande and Lambityeco, Mitla, and El Palmillo in the eastern Tlacolula arm. The latter is the focus of an ongoing project by Gary Feinman and Linda Nicholas of Chicago\'s Field Museum. By the end of the same period (ca. AD 900-1000), the ancient capital was largely abandoned. The once powerful Monte Albán state was replaced by dozens of competing smaller polities, a situation that lasted up to the Spanish conquest.</string>


    <string name="overview_mitla">Mitla is the second-most important archeological site in the state of Oaxaca in Mexico, and the most important of the Zapotec culture. The site is located 44 km east from the city of Oaxaca, in the upper end of the Tlacolula Valley, one of the three cold, high valleys that form the Central Valleys Region of the state. At an elevation of 4,855 ft (1,480 m), surrounded by the mountains of the Sierra Madre del Sur, the archeological site is within the modern municipality of San Pablo Villa de Mitla. It is 24 mi (38 km) southeast of Oaxaca city. While Monte Albán was the most important politically of the Zapotec centers, Mitla became the main religious one in a later period as the area became dominated by the Mixtec.\n\n
The name Mitla is derived from the Nahuatl name Mictlán, meaning the \"place of the dead\" or \"underworld". Its Zapotec name is Lyobaa, which means \“place of rest”. The name Mictlán was Hispanicized or transliterated to Mitla by the Spanish colonists. It was established as a sacred burial site by the Zapotec, but the architecture and designs also show the influence of the Mixtec, who had become prominent in the area during the peak of Mitla settlement.\n\n
Mitla is unique among Mesoamerican sites because of its elaborate and intricate mosaic fretwork and geometric designs that cover tombs, panels, friezes, and even entire walls of the complex. These mosaics are made with small, finely cut and polished stone pieces that have been fitted together without the use of mortar. No other site in Mexico has this decorative work.</string>


    <string name="history_mitla">Mitla is one of many well-preserved archeological sites in the Oaxaca Valley, where the cold, dry climate has conserved sites as old as 10,000 years. This valley was settled by the Zapotec before the turn of the first millennium, who over the centuries developed a hierarchical society governed by elites. While the valley was relatively isolated, the Zapotec did have contacts with other Mesoamerican peoples. This has been demonstrated by cultural, pottery and other influences that flowed back and forth between other peoples.
By the time the Spanish arrived in the 16th century, the Mixtec had migrated into the area. The mixed Zapotec state had a population of more than 500,000. They had developed and used sophisticated construction techniques, a writing system, two calendar systems, and sophisticated systems of agricultural cultivation. Their basic crops were maize, beans, squash, and chili peppers. These were dependent on their constructed irrigation systems and the use of terraces on mountain slopes in order to grow food for the mostly urban population.\n\n
Mitla was inhabited at least since the Classic Period (100-650 CE) and perhaps from as early as 900 BCE. It began as a fortified village on the outer edge of the valley and later became the main religious center of the Zapotec. The Mixtec took control of the area around 1000 CE, although the area remained populated by many Zapotec. The city reached its height and largest size between 750 and 1521, with both Zapotec and Mixtec influences in its architecture during that time.\n\n
Mitla is one of the pre-Columbian sites that express the Mesoamerican belief that death was the most consequential part of life after birth. It was built as a gateway between the world of the living and the world of the dead. Nobles buried at Mitla were believed to be destined to become \“cloud people\” who would intercede on behalf of the population below.\n\n
Mitla was still occupied and functioning as the main religious center when the Spanish explorers and military expeditions arrived in the 1520s and later. The high priest, called the Uija-tào, resided at Mitla. The Spanish likened him to the pope of the Catholic Church. At that time the urban center covered an area of 1 to 2 square kilometres (0.39 to 0.77 sq mi), with suburban areas surrounding it. In the rural areas, intensive agriculture was practiced over an area of more than 20 square kilometres (7.7 sq mi) to feed the city.\n\n
During the early colonial period, some of the best descriptions of the site were documented by the Spanish soldiers and missionaries who first arrived in the valley. Friar Toribio de Benavente Motolina wrote about the city in the mid-16th century, and was one of the first to do so. He said that its name meant \“hell\” his interpretation of the underworld. Another early writer was Diego García de Palacio, a Spanish nautical engineer working in Mexico and Guatemala, whose account was dated in 1576.\n\n
In 1553 Oaxacan Archbishop Albuquerque ordered the destruction of the Mitlan site. As the site had long held great political and religious significance for the area, he wanted to dissolve its power. Spanish-directed forces attacked the buildings, dismantling and sacking them, with few buildings spared. Later, Spanish clergy lived in some of the rooms of the sacred site, to displace the Zapotec who had been there before.\n\n
The stone blocks and remains were used as building materials for Spanish churches, including the Church of San Pablo, which was constructed on top of part of the ruins. The north side of the Cathedral of Oaxaca incorporates design features from Mitla to symbolize that the old culture was superseded by the new religious order.\n\n
In the state of Oaxaca, Mitla is second in importance as an archeological site only to Monte Albán, the central city. At the beginning of the 20th century, the government of Porfirio Díaz chose Mitla as one of the emblematic symbols of pre-Hispanic Mexico for the Centennial celebrations of Mexico\’s Independence. Alfonso Caso, the archaeologist who excavated Monte Albán in 1931, also did work at Mitla in the 1920s and 1930s.\n\n
Since the 1980s, Mitla has been the site of further excavations, with important work conducted on the North Group. The colonial church was excavated around the start of the 21st century. For Mexico\'s bicentennial celebrations in 2010, INAH has been intensifying efforts to conserve the ancient ruins.\n\n

</string>


    <string name="overview_palenque">Palenque also anciently known as Lakamha (literally: \"Big Water\"), was a Maya city state in southern Mexico that flourished in the 7th century. The Palenque ruins date from ca. 226 BC to ca. 799 AD.[citation needed] After its decline, it was overgrown by the jungle of cedar, mahogany, and sapodilla trees, but has since been excavated and restored. It is located near the Usumacinta River in the Mexican state of Chiapas, about 130 km (81 mi) south of Ciudad del Carmen, 150 meters (490 ft) above sea level. It averages a humid 26 °C (79 °F) with roughly 2,160 millimeters (85 in) of rain a year.\n\n
Palenque is a medium-sized site, smaller than Tikal, Chichen Itza, or Copán, but it contains some of the finest architecture, sculpture, roof comb and bas-relief carvings that the Mayas produced. Much of the history of Palenque has been reconstructed from reading the hieroglyphic inscriptions on the many monuments. Historians now have a long sequence of the ruling dynasty of Palenque in the 5th century and extensive knowledge of the city-state\'s rivalry with other states such as Calakmul and Toniná. The most famous ruler of Palenque was K\'inich Janaab Pakal, or Pacal the Great, whose tomb has been found and excavated in the Temple of the Inscriptions.\n\n
By 2005, the discovered area covered up to 2.5 km2 (1 sq mi), but it is estimated that less than 10% of the total area of the city is explored, leaving more than a thousand structures still covered by jungle. Palenque received 920,470 visitors in 2017.
</string>


    <string name="history_palenque">Mythological beings using a variety of emblem glyphs in their titles suggests a complex early history. For instance, Kʼukʼ Bahlam I, the supposed founder of the Palenque dynasty, is called a Toktan Ajaw in the text of the Temple of the Foliated Cross.\n\n
The famous structures that we know today probably represent a rebuilding effort in response to the attacks by the city of Calakmul and its client states in 599 and 611. One of the main figures responsible for rebuilding Palenque and for a renaissance in the city\'s art and architecture is also one of the best-known Maya Ajaw, Kʼinich Janaabʼ Pakal (Pacal the Great), who ruled from 615 to 683. He is known through his funerary monument dubbed the Temple of Inscriptions, after the lengthy text preserved in the temple\'s superstructure. At the time Alberto Ruz Lhuillier excavated Pakal\'s tomb, it was the richest and best preserved of any scientifically excavated burial then known from the ancient Americas. It held this position until the discovery of the rich Moche burials at Sipan, Peru and the recent discoveries at Copan and Calakmul.\n\n
Beside the attention that K\'inich Janaab\' Pakal\'s tomb brought to Palenque, the city is historically significant for its extensive hieroglyphic corpus composed during the reigns of Janaab\' Pakal, his son Kʼinich Kan Bahlam II, and his grandson K\'inich Akal Mo\' Naab\', and for being the location where Heinrich Berlin and later Linda Schele and Peter Mathews outlined the first dynastic list for any Maya city. The work of Tatiana Proskouriakoff as well as that of Berlin, Schele, Mathews, and others, initiated the intense historical investigations that characterized much of the scholarship on the ancient Maya from the 1960s to the present. The extensive iconography and textual corpus has also allowed for study of Classic period Maya mythology and ritual practice.\n\n
EARLY CLASSIC PERIOD\n\n
The first ajaw, or king, of B\'aakal that we know of was K\'uk Balam (Quetzal Jaguar), who governed for four years starting in the year 431. After him, a king came to power, nicknamed \"Casper\" by archaeologists. The next two kings were probably Casper\'s sons. Little was known about the first of these, B\'utz Aj Sak Chiik, until 1994, when a tablet was found describing a ritual for the king. The first tablet mentioned his successor Ahkal Mo\' Naab I as a teenage prince, and therefore it is believed that there was a family relation between them. For unknown reasons, Akhal Mo\' Naab I had great prestige, so the kings who succeeded him were proud to be his descendants.\n\n
When Ahkal Mo\' Naab I died in 524, there was an interregnum of four years, before the following king was crowned at Toktán in 529. K\'an Joy Chitam I governed for 36 years. His sons Ahkal Mo\' Naab II and K\'an B\'alam I were the first kings who used the title Kinich, which means \"the great sun\". This word was used also by later kings. B\'alam was succeeded in 583 by Yohl Ik\'nal, who was supposedly his daughter. The inscriptions found in Palenque document a battle that occurred under her government in which troops from Calakmul invaded and sacked Palenque, a military feat without known precedents. These events took place in 599.\n\n
A second victory by Calakmul occurred some twelve years later, in 611, under the government of Aj Ne\' Yohl Mat, son of Yohl Iknal. In this occasion, the king of Calakmul entered Palenque in person, consolidating a significant military disaster, which was followed by an epoch of political disorder. Aj Ne\' Yohl Mat was to die in 612.\n\n
LATE CLASSIC PERIOD\n\n
B\'aakal began the Late Classic period in the throes of the disorder created by the defeats before Calakmul. The glyphic panels at the Temple of Inscriptions, which records the events at this time, relates that some fundamental annual religious ceremonies were not performed in 613, and at this point states: \"Lost is the divine lady, lost is the king.\" Mentions of the government at the time have not been found.\n\n
It is believed that after the death of Aj Ne\' Yohl Mat, Janaab Pakal, also called Pakal I, took power thanks to a political agreement. Janaab Pakal assumed the functions of the ajaw (king) but never was crowned. He was succeeded in 612 by his daughter, the queen Sak K\'uk\', who governed for only three years until her son was old enough to rule. It is considered that the dynasty was reestablished from then on, so B\'aakal retook the path of glory and splendor.\n\n
The grandson of Janaab Pakal is the most famous of the Mayan kings, K\'inich Janaab\' Pakal, also known as Pakal the Great. He began rule at the age of 12 years after his mother Sak Kuk resigned as queen after three years, thus passing power on to him. Pakal the Great reigned in Palenque from 615 to 683, and his mother remained an important force for the first 25 years of his rule. She may have ruled jointly with him. Known as the favorite of the gods, he carried Palenque to new levels of splendor, in spite of having come to power when the city was at a low point. Pakal married the princess of Oktán, Lady Tzakbu Ajaw (also known as Ahpo-Hel) in 624 and had at least three children.\n\n
Most of the palaces and temples of Palenque were constructed during his government and the city flourished as never before, eclipsing Tikal. The central complex, known as The Palace, was enlarged and remodeled on various occasions, notably in the years 654, 661, and 668. In this structure, is a text describing how in that epoch Palenque was newly allied with Tikal, and also with Yaxchilan, and that they were able to capture the six enemy kings of the alliance. Not much more had been translated from the text.\n\n
After the death of Pakal in 683, his older son K\'inich Kan B\'alam assumed the kingship of B\'aakal, who in turn was succeeded in 702 by his brother K\'inich K\'an Joy Chitam II. The first continued the architectural and sculptural works that were begun by his father, as well as finishing the construction of the famous tomb of Pakal. Pakal\'s sarcophagus, built for a very tall man, held the richest collection of jade seen in a Mayan tomb. A jade mosaic mask was placed over his face, and a suit made of jade adorned his body, with each piece hand-carved and held together by gold wire.\n\n
Furthermore, K\'inich Kan B\'alam I began ambitious projects, including the Group of the Crosses. Thanks to numerous works begun during his government, now we have portraits of this king, found in various sculptures. His brother succeeded him continuing with the same enthusiasm of construction and art, reconstructing and enlarging the north side of the Palace. Thanks to the reign of these three kings, B\'aakal had a century of growing and splendor.\n\n
In 711, Palenque was sacked by the realm of Toniná, and the old king K\'inich K\'an Joy Chitam II was taken prisoner. It is not known what the final fate of the king was, and it is presumed that he was executed in Toniná. For 10 years there was no king. Finally, K\'inich Ahkal Mo\' Nab\' III was crowned in 722. Although the new king belonged to the royalty, there is no evidence that he was the direct inheritor direct of K\'inich K\'an Joy Chitam II. It is believed, therefore, that this coronation was a break in the dynastic line, and probably K\'inich Ahkal Nab\' arrived to power after years of maneuvering and forging political alliances. This king, his son, and grandson governed until the end of the 8th century. Little is known about this period, except that, among other events, the war with Toniná continued, where there are hieroglyphics that record a new defeat of Palenque.\n\n
Occasionally city-state lords were women. Lady Sak Kuk ruled at Palenque for at least three years starting in 612 CE, before she passed her title to her son. However, these female rulers were accorded male attributes. Thus, these women became more masculine as they assumed roles that were typically male roles.\n\n
ABANDONMENT\n\n
During the 8th century, B\'aakal came under increasing stress, in concert with most other Classic Mayan city-states, and there was no new elite construction in the ceremonial center sometime after 800. An agricultural population continued to live here for a few generations, then the site was abandoned and was slowly grown over by the forest. The district was very sparsely populated when the Spanish first arrived in the 1520s.
</string>


    <string name="overview_uxmal">Uxmal (Yucatec Maya: Óoxmáal) is an ancient Maya city of the classical period located in present-day Mexico. It is considered one of the most important archaeological sites of Maya culture, along with Palenque, Chichén, and Calakmul in Mexico, Caracol and Xunantunich in Belize, and Tikal in Guatemala. It is located in the Puuc region of the eastern Yucatan Peninsula, and is considered one of the Maya cities most representative of the region\'s dominant architectural style. It has been designated a UNESCO World Heritage Site in recognition of its significance.\n\n
    It is located 62 km south of Mérida, capital of Yucatán state in Mexico. Its buildings are noted for their size and decoration. Ancient roads called sacbes connect the buildings, and also were built to other cities in the area such as Chichén Itzá in modern-day Mexico, Caracol and Xunantunich in modern-day Belize, and Tikal in modern-day Guatemala.\n\n
    Its buildings are typical of the Puuc style, with smooth low walls that open on ornate friezes based on representations of typical Maya huts. These are represented by columns (representing the reeds used for the walls of the huts) and trapezoidal shapes (representing the thatched roofs). Entwined snakes and, in many cases two-headed snakes are used for masks of the rain god, Chaac; its big noses represent the rays of the storms. Feathered serpents with open fangs are shown leaving from the same human beings. Also seen in some cities are the influences of the Nahua, who followed the cult of Quetzalcoatl and Tlaloc. These were integrated with the original elements of the Puuc tradition.\n\n
    The buildings take advantage of the terrain to gain height and acquire important volumes, including the Pyramid of the Magician, with five levels, and the Governor\'s Palace, which covers an area of more than 1,200 m2 (12,917 sq ft).</string>


    <string name="history_uxmal">The present name seems to derive from Oxmal, meaning \"three times built.\" This seems to refer to the site\'s antiquity and the times it had to rebuild. The etymology is disputed. Another possibility is Uchmal which means \"what is to come, the future\". By tradition, this was supposed to be an \"invisible city\" built in one night by the magic of the dwarf king.\n\n
    While much work has been done at the popular tourist destination of Uxmal to consolidate and restore buildings, little in the way of serious archeological excavation and research has been done. The city\'s dates of occupation are unknown and the estimated population (about 15,000 people) is a rough guess. Most of the city\'s major construction took place while Uxmal was the capital of a Late Classic Maya state around 850-925 AD. After about 1000 AD, Toltec invaders took over, and most building ceased by 1100 AD.\n\n
    Maya chronicles say that Uxmal was founded about 500 A.D. by Hun Uitzil Chac Tutul Xiu. For generations Uxmal was ruled over by the Xiu family. It was the most powerful site in western Yucatán, and for a while, in alliance with Chichen Itza, dominated all of the northern Maya area. Sometime after about 1200, no new major construction seems to have been made at Uxmal, possibly related to the fall of Uxmal\'s ally Chichen Itza and the shift of power in Yucatán to Mayapan. The Xiu moved their capital to Maní, and the population of Uxmal declined.\n\n
    Uxmal was dominant from 875 to 900 CE. The site appears to have been the capital of a regional state in the Puuc region from 850-950 CE. The Maya dynasty expanded their dominion over their neighbors. This prominence did not last long, as the population dispersed around 1000 CE.\n\n
    After the Spanish conquest of Yucatán (in which the Xiu allied with the Spanish), early colonial documents suggest that Uxmal was still an inhabited place of some importance into the 1550s. As the Spanish did not build a town here, Uxmal was soon after largely abandoned.</string>


    <string name="overview_chichen_itza">Chichen Itza was a large pre-Columbian city built by the Maya people of the Terminal Classic period. The archaeological site is located in Tinúm Municipality, Yucatán State, Mexico.\n\n
    Chichen Itza was a major focal point in the Northern Maya Lowlands from the Late Classic (c. AD 600–900) through the Terminal Classic (c. AD 800–900) and into the early portion of the Postclassic period (c. AD 900–1200). The site exhibits a multitude of architectural styles, reminiscent of styles seen in central Mexico and of the Puuc and Chenes styles of the Northern Maya lowlands. The presence of central Mexican styles was once thought to have been representative of direct migration or even conquest from central Mexico, but most contemporary interpretations view the presence of these non-Maya styles more as the result of cultural diffusion.\n\n
    Chichen Itza was one of the largest Maya cities and it was likely to have been one of the mythical great cities, or Tollans, referred to in later Mesoamerican literature. The city may have had the most diverse population in the Maya world, a factor that could have contributed to the variety of architectural styles at the site.\n\n
    The ruins of Chichen Itza are federal property, and the site\'s stewardship is maintained by Mexico\'s Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia (National Institute of Anthropology and History). The land under the monuments had been privately owned until 29 March 2010, when it was purchased by the state of Yucatán.\n\n
    Chichen Itza is one of the most visited archaeological sites in Mexico with over 2.6 million tourists in 2017.</string>


    <string name="history_chichen_itza">The Maya name \"Chichen Itza" means "At the mouth of the well of the Itza\". This derives from chi\', meaning \"mouth\" or \"edge\", and chʼen or chʼeʼen, meaning \"well\". Itzá is the name of an ethnic-lineage group that gained political and economic dominance of the northern peninsula. One possible translation for Itza is \"enchanter (or enchantment) of the wate\", from its (itz), \"sorcerer\", and ha, \"water\".\n\n
The name is spelled Chichén Itzá in Spanish, and the accents are sometimes maintained in other languages to show that both parts of the name are stressed on their final syllable. Other references prefer the Maya orthography, Chichʼen Itzaʼ (pronounced [tʃitʃʼen itsáʔ]). This form preserves the phonemic distinction between chʼ and ch, since the base word chʼeʼen (which, however, is not stressed in Maya) begins with a postalveolar ejective affricate consonant. The word \"Itzaʼ\" has a high tone on the \"a\" followed by a glottal stop (indicated by the apostrophe).\n\n
Evidence in the Chilam Balam books indicates another, earlier name for this city prior to the arrival of the Itza hegemony in northern Yucatán. While most sources agree the first word means seven, there is considerable debate as to the correct translation of the rest. This earlier name is difficult to define because of the absence of a single standard of orthography, but it is represented variously as Uuc Yabnal (\"Seven Great House\"), Uuc Hab Nal (\"Seven Bushy Places\"), Uucyabnal (\"Seven Great Rulers\") or Uc Abnal (\"Seven Lines of Abnal\"). This name, dating to the Late Classic Period, is recorded both in the book of Chilam Balam de Chumayel and in hieroglyphic texts in the ruins.\n\n
The layout of Chichen Itza site core developed during its earlier phase of occupation, between 750 and 900 AD. Its final layout was developed after 900 AD, and the 10th century saw the rise of the city as a regional capital controlling the area from central Yucatán to the north coast, with its power extending down the east and west coasts of the peninsula. The earliest hieroglyphic date discovered at Chichen Itza is equivalent to 832 AD, while the last known date was recorded in the Osario temple in 998.\n\n
ESTABLISHMENT\n\n
The Late Classic city was centered upon the area to the southwest of the Xtoloc cenote, with the main architecture represented by the substructures now underlying the Las Monjas and Observatorio and the basal platform upon which they were built.\n\n
ASCENDANCY\n\n
Chichen Itza rose to regional prominence toward the end of the Early Classic period (roughly 600 AD). It was, however, toward the end of the Late Classic and into the early part of the Terminal Classic that the site became a major regional capital, centralizing and dominating political, sociocultural, economic, and ideological life in the northern Maya lowlands. The ascension of Chichen Itza roughly correlates with the decline and fragmentation of the major centers of the southern Maya lowlands.\n\n
As Chichen Itza rose to prominence, the cities of Yaxuna (to the south) and Coba (to the east) were suffering decline. These two cities had been mutual allies, with Yaxuna dependent upon Coba. At some point in the 10th century Coba lost a significant portion of its territory, isolating Yaxuna, and Chichen Itza may have directly contributed to the collapse of both cities.\n\n
DECLINE\n\n
According to some colonial Mayan sources (e.g., the Book of Chilam Balam of Chumayel), Hunac Ceel, ruler of Mayapan, conquered Chichen Itza in the 13th century. Hunac Ceel supposedly prophesied his own rise to power. According to custom at the time, individuals thrown into the Cenote Sagrado were believed to have the power of prophecy if they survived. During one such ceremony, the chronicles state, there were no survivors, so Hunac Ceel leaped into the Cenote Sagrado, and when removed, prophesied his own ascension.\n\n
While there is some archaeological evidence that indicates Chichén Itzá was at one time looted and sacked, there appears to be greater evidence that it could not have been by Mayapan, at least not when Chichén Itzá was an active urban center. Archaeological data now indicates that Chichen Itza declined as a regional center by 1100, before the rise of Mayapan. Ongoing research at the site of Mayapan may help resolve this chronological conundrum.\n\n
After Chichén Itzá elite activities ceased, the city may not have been abandoned. When the Spanish arrived, they found a thriving local population, although it is not clear from Spanish sources if these Maya were living in Chichen Itza proper, or a nearby settlement. The relatively high population density in the region was a factor in the conquistadors\' decision to locate a capital there. According to post-Conquest sources, both Spanish and Maya, the Cenote Sagrado remained a place of pilgrimage.</string>


    <string name="overview_tulum">Tulum is the site of a pre-Columbian Mayan walled city which served as a major port for Coba, in the Mexican state of Quintana Roo. The ruins are situated on 12-meter (39 ft) tall cliffs along the east coast of the Yucatán Peninsula on the Caribbean Sea in the state of Quintana Roo, Mexico. Tulum was one of the last cities built and inhabited by the Maya. It was at its height between the 13th and 15th centuries and managed to survive about 70 years after the Spanish began occupying Mexico. Old World diseases brought by the Spanish settlers appear to have resulted in very high fatalities, disrupting the society, and eventually causing the city to be abandoned. One of the best-preserved coastal Maya sites, Tulum is today a popular site for tourists</string>


    <string name="history_tulum">The site might have been called Zama, meaning City of Dawn, because it faces the sunrise. Tulum stands on a bluff facing east toward the Caribbean Sea. Tulúm is also the Yucatán Mayan word for fence, wall or trench. The walls surrounding the site allowed the Tulum fort to be defended against invasions. Tulum had access to both land and sea trade routes, making it an important trade hub, especially for obsidian. From numerous depictions in murals and other works around the site, Tulum appears to have been an important site for the worship of the Diving or Descending god.\\n
Tulum was first mentioned by Juan Díaz, a member of Juan de Grijalva\'s Spanish expedition of 1518, the first Europeans to spot Tulum. The first detailed description of the ruins was published by John Lloyd Stephens and Frederick Catherwood in 1843 in the book Incidents of Travel in Yucatan. As they arrived from the sea, Stephens and Catherwood first saw a tall building that impressed them greatly, most likely the great Castillo of the site. They made accurate maps of the site\'s walls, and Catherwood made sketches of the Castillo and several other buildings. Stephens and Catherwood also reported an early classic stele at the site, with an inscribed date of AD 564 (now in the British Museum\'s collection). This has been interpreted as meaning that the stele was likely built elsewhere and brought to Tulum to be reused.\n\n
Work conducted at Tulum continued with that of Sylvanus Morley and George P. Howe, beginning in 1913. They worked to restore and open the public beaches. The work was continued by the Carnegie Institution from 1916 to 1922, Samuel Lothrop in 1924 who also mapped the site, Miguel Ángel Fernández in the late 1930s and early 1940s, William Sanders in 1956, and then later in the 1970s by Arthur G. Miller. Through these later investigations done by Sanders and Miller, it has been determined that Tulum was occupied during the late Postclassic period around AD 1200. The site continued to be occupied until contact with the Spanish was made in the early 16th century. By the end of the 16th century, the site was abandoned completely.\n\n</string>


    <string name="curiosidades_tulum">
In 2020, an underwater archaeological expedition led by Jerónimo Avilés again excavated the cave and revealed the skeleton of a female about 30 years of age that lived at least 9,900 years ago. According to craniometric measurements, the skull is believed to conform to the mesocephalic pattern, like the other three skulls found in Tulum caves. Three different scars on the skull of the woman showed that she was hit with something hard and her skull bones were broken. Her skull also had crater-like deformations and tissue deformities that appeared to be caused by a bacterial relative of syphilis.\n\n
According to study lead researcher Wolfgang Stinnesbeck, \"It really looks as if this woman had a very hard time and an extremely unhappy end of her life. Obviously, this is speculative, but given the traumas and the pathological deformations on her skull, it appears a likely scenario that she may have been expelled from her group and was killed in the cave, or was left in the cave to die there\”.\n\n
The newly discovered skeleton was 140 meters away from the Chan Hol 2 site. Although archaeologists assumed the divers found the remains of the missing Chan Hol 2, the analysis proved that these assumptions were erroneous in a short time. Stinnesbeck compared the new bones to old photographs of Chan Hol 2 and showed that the two skeletons represent different individuals.\n\n
Due to their distinctive features, study co-researcher Samuel Rennie suggest the existence of at least two morphologically diverse groups of people living separately in Mexico during the transition from Pleistocene to Holocene.</string>


    <string name="snippet_teotihuacan">Discovered: known to pre-columbian civilizations\nand first european conquerors</string>
    <string name="snippet_cholula">Discovered: known to pre-columbian civilizations\nand first european conquerors</string>
    <string name="snippet_monte_alban">Discovered: known to pre-columbian civilizations\nand first european conquerors</string>
    <string name="snippet_mitla">Discovered: known to pre-columbian civilizations\nand first european conquerors</string>
    <string name="snippet_palenque">1773 - Ramón de Ordoñez y Aguilar</string>
    <string name="snippet_uxmal">1573 - Diego de Landa</string>
    <string name="snippet_chichen_itza">1532 - Fransisco de Montejo del Mozo</string>
    <string name="snippet_tulum">1518 - Juan Diaz</string>

    <string name="snippet_cdmx">Population: 9 209 944\nAltitude: 2240m n.p.m\nFoundation: 1521</string>
    <string name="snippet_taxco">Population: 50 399\nAltitude: 1778m n.p.m\nFoundation: 1529</string>
    <string name="snippet_acapulco">Population: 658 609\nAltitude: 30m n.p.m\nFoundation: 1550</string>
    <string name="snippet_puebla">Population: 1 576 259\nAltitude: 21358m n.p.m\nFoundation: 1531</string>
    <string name="snippet_oaxaca">Population: 300 050\nAltitude: 1555m n.p.m\nFoundation: 1532</string>
    <string name="snippet_san_cristobal">Population: 185 917\nAltitude: 2200m n.p.m\nFoundation: 1528</string>
    <string name="snippet_campeche">Population: 249 623\nAltitude: 3m n.p.m\nFoundation: 1540</string>
    <string name="snippet_merida">Population: 921 771\nAltitude: 14m n.p.m\nFoundation: 1542</string>
    <string name="snippet_queretaro">Population: 1 049 777\nAltitude: 1820m n.p.m\nFoundation: 1531</string>
    <string name="snippet_cancun">Population: 888 797\nAltitude: 11m n.p.m\nFoundation: 1970</string>

    <string name="snippet_celestun">Celestun Biosphere Reserve, 600km\²</string>
    <string name="snippet_sumidero"></string>
    <string name="snippet_agua_azul"></string>
    <string name="snippet_misol_ha"></string>
    <string name="snippet_tule"></string>
    <string name="snippet_cacahuamilpa"></string>
    <string name="snippet_eiypantla"></string>
    <string name="snippet_hierve_el_agua"></string>



    <string-array name="zones">
        <item>Teotihuacan</item>
        <item>Cholula</item>
        <item>Monte Alban</item>
        <item>Mitla</item>
        <item>Palenque</item>
        <item>Uxmal</item>
        <item>Chichen Itza</item>
        <item>Tulum</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="cities">
        <item>CDMX</item>
        <item>Taxco</item>
        <item>Acapulco</item>
        <item>Puebla</item>
        <item>Oaxaca</item>
        <item>San Cristobal</item>
        <item>Campeche</item>
        <item>Merida</item>
        <item>Queretaro</item>
        <item>Cancun</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="natures">
        <item>Celestun</item>
        <item>Sumidero</item>
        <item>Aqua Azul</item>
        <item>Misol-Ha</item>
        <item>Tule</item>
        <item>Cacahuamilpa</item>
        <item>Eiypantla</item>
        <item>Hierve el Agua</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="titles">
        <item>Ekran Główny</item>
        <item>Strefy Archeologiczne</item>
        <item>Miasta</item>
        <item>Parki</item>
    </string-array>

    <!-- TODO: Remove or change this placeholder text -->
    <string name="hello_blank_fragment">Hello blank fragment</string>
    <string name="hello_world">hello</string>
    <string name="title_activity_maps"></string>
    <string name="mapa">Mapa</string>
</resources>